<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the faithfull and true-hearted covenanters, vvhich are the noble Philadelphians. A diurnall, of the desires and indeavours of one that earnestly desires the advancement of the cause of Christ. B.W. of Darbie. Reade all or none.</title>
            <author>B. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E257_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210039</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868874</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97064)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 44:E257[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the faithfull and true-hearted covenanters, vvhich are the noble Philadelphians. A diurnall, of the desires and indeavours of one that earnestly desires the advancement of the cause of Christ. B.W. of Darbie. Reade all or none.</title>
                  <author>B. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Covenanters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121230:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO THE FAITHFULL AND TRUE-HEARTED Covenanters, VVHICH ARE THE NOBLE Philadelphians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diurnall,</hi> Of the Deſires and Indeavours of one that ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſires the advancement of the Cauſe of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B. W.</hi> Of DARBIE.</p>
            <p>Reade all or none.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London Printed.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:121230:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121230:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the faithfull and true hearted COVENANTERS: I</hi> Deſire to preſent unto you this little Diurnall of my poore indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and deſires for the advancement of the cauſe of Chriſt, ſince the firſt call of this hononurable Parliament, which must ſit till the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of Poperie, Idolatrie and Willworſhip.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt of all, at the Election of the Knights for Darbyſhire, after the long debating of the matter, the Town being not ſo convenient, they went into a peece of ground called the <hi>Hulmes,</hi> and after ſome time ſpent there, it growing towards dinner time, and great Dinners provided, they began to draw away; I went to Sir <hi>Iohn Curſon,</hi> he being on the top of a little hill with Mr. <hi>Manners</hi> and divers other Gentlemen; where I requeſted theſe three things of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they would not leave us till ſuch time as we had made them ſure. Secondly, that Proclamation might be made that all thoſe that were for Sir <hi>Iohn Curſon,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Manners</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire unto them into the <hi>Hulmes.</hi> Thirdly, that Robert <hi>Bennet</hi> who kept the Records of convicted Papiſts, might bring them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as the Papiſts came to give their votes, we would reward them according to their deſerts, and ſend them away; for I tould them that Papiſts had no vote in the election of Knights: All this was granted; and witneſſe Sir <hi>Iohn Curſon</hi> and divers there, whether God in mercy did not make theſe requeſts effectuall for accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of what we were there met together for: and I am ſure I was ſoundly threatned by ſome in Darbie, they telling mee that I had made the worſt daies worke for my ſelfe, that ever I did in all my life, but if the Lord pleaſe he can make it the beſt: Its true, that after the laſt requeſt was made knowne: Papiſts that came to vote for one man, whoſe name I omit to mention, fled out of the towne as faſt as they could, I would they would packe as faſt out of the Kingdome, for they have, and ever will be enemies to the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121230:3"/>
And at the Election of the Burgeſſes for the Town of Derbie, I thinke my endeavours were not wanting therein, as either one or both can witneſſe: but for the Recorder he turned Delinquent: for his Records I doubt they are gone, and for the Evidences of his lands they will do him little Good, except he come in to make his peace, according to the laſt Declaration ſet ſet forth by both Kingdmes.</p>
            <p>After this I doe confeſſe I had a long time of reſt, wherein I might have followed my calling to have advanced ſomething for my good wife, and four ſweet children, but truly I had no power to do almoſt any thing but hearken for newes, concerning the good ſucceſſe of this honourable Parliament; The continuation of Newes was ſuch, that many ſaid they were perſwaded there would be a ſpeedy and peaceable Reformation, I ever replying, that if there were a ſound and thorow Reformation without ſhedding of blood, it would be ſuch a thing as ſelldome had been heard of, alleaging this, that the Divell ſeeing his Kingdome to begin to fall ſo faſt, would not be wanting to ſtir up divelliſh and Malignant ſpirits to do what miſchief they could, and it is apparent, they have not been wanting: But it may be truely ſaid, that the pits they have digged for others, they have fallen into themſelues, and ſurely the Biſhops cannot chuſe before this time but to have wiſhed that they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the wholſome advice of Mr. <hi>Brightman,</hi> to have repented, and made themſelves in equall rancke to their fellow brethren, and not to Lord it over Gods heritage, they have had this forty yeers to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in and yet have not repented. For it is too well known they were like Princes, and you know, that if pride get into the heart, it is an hard thing to get it out; and I know, that except they repent and make themſelves in equall rancke with their fellow brethren, they muſt fall and never riſe againe: As for Papiſts, one would think that they before now ſhould wiſh they had ſate ſtill with the third part of their eſtates, &amp; have left off plotting, &amp; contriving miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe againſt King, Parliament, and Kingdome, becuaſe of the ill ſucceſſe they have had in all places, and at all times in their wicked and Devilliſh deſignes: but the foudation of their Religion being laid upon the great ſins of the world, that is, Killing Chriſtian Kings, blowing up of Parliaments, and deſtroying of Gods people, which they call Hereticks, it is a thing not to be wondred at: For as the old ſaying is, the Devils Children, the Devils nature: But they being fallen into the pit they digged for others, ſome of them, with ſome other Incendiaries of the Kingdome like the Frogs of Egypt, except into the Kings chamber, &amp; would never ſuffer him to have reſt, til they had gotten him to the City of Yorke, to take up his ſtands: I hearing of it went to Newarke, where I ſaw his Majeſtie, and returned home again, I relating what I had ſeen, and what I thought, namely, that I ſaw the King, who looked very pale, as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121230:3"/>though he were much troubled in minde, and thought that the Queene, the Papiſts, and Prelaticall faction, had prevailedd with the King to do that which was a great trouble unto him: and I ſuppoſe here was a great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the great troubles of this Kingdome, yet here ſtands the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of Gods people, that all things doe and ſhall worke for their good.</p>
            <p>My next indeavour, according to my poor ability, was, to buy ſome Armes, which I did accordingly, for I thought there would be great uſe for them, ſeeing a little cloude riſing in the North like unto a mans hand, which would have ſpread it ſelfe over all the Kingdome, had not God in his mercy prevented it: And herein I can never ſufficiently ſet forth the honour due to Sir <hi>Iohn Gell,</hi> for his love, courage, and zeale, for maintenance of the truth, to the Town and Countie of Darbie; for had but ſome Gentlemen made good their promiſe unto him, he had endeavoured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the cloude, that no part of it had come into Darbieſhiere.</p>
            <p>But ſo it was, that his Majeſtie came to Nottingham to ſet up his Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and the day being made known, many Darby men came thither and ſhewed themſelves before the King in a bodie, for fear leſt they ſhould ſuffer in a good cauſe, I met even then with an honeſt Citizen (who was my neighbour formerly in Nottingham) that was ſent as Meſſenger from the Parliament, the private conference hee and I had I paſſe by, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſhewed him ſome reaſons that it was no hard thing with 200. men to ſurprize the Caſtle and the Magazine, that it might deſtroy none of Gods people. But the Standard going up to be reared, I went to ſee the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of it; It did much reſemble blood and gold, I hardly ſaw any man ſo buſie as Sir <hi>Iacob Aſhley,</hi> evill Commanders matters not to ſhed inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood, ſo they can get gold, neither will they be wanting to ſpinne forth the Kingdomes miſery: But reared it was, and after that the Cloud grew to that greatneſſe, that it reached from Nottingham to Darby, and ſo to Hopton, where there was ſuch a divelliſh ſtorme in it, that it tooke away all that was in Sir <hi>Iohn Gells</hi> houſe, I thinke ſaving onely a man and a maide; the newes whereof preſently came to Coventrie to Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> and he ſeeing an honeſt Miniſter, that I love well, called him unto him, and told him the newes, he anſwered, and ſaid he was heartily ſorry, but Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe anſwered him againe, and proteſted that it did not trouble him a jot, as the Miniſter after told mee: truely Gods providence is much ſeen in divers places, where I have beene, to keep up the hearts of Multitudes that wiſh well to the Cauſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great Croſſes of this nature, God is alwaies as good as his promiſe, and he will ſupport his own people in time of their greateſt troubles: After that the King came to Darbie, whom I pray God to bleſſe in all lawfull deſignes, and to make his Crowne to flowriſh upon him, and his poſterity after him: Proclamation was made upon paine of death to bring in all their armes, ſome men were obſerved to carry them willingly, and others unwillingly, ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt faithfull men kept theirs, but the reſt would learn wiſedome of Sir <hi>Iohn Gell,</hi> who valued his armes more then his eſtate, for truely the cauſe being well conſidered, the loſſe of armes in a houſe, is more then the loſſe of the houſe it ſelfe, and the loſſe of the armes in a garriſon towne is more then the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121230:4"/>loſſe of the towne it ſelfe: For if the Devill and Papiſts could have had as many arms as they would have had, what had become of Proteſtants before this day? But herein take notice of the Parliaments care of the Magazine; for my own part, I would carry in none, for my beleefe was and is, that armes being put into Papiſts hands cannot be imployed for the good of the King, Kingdome, or proteſtant religion.</p>
            <p>Not very long after, Sir <hi>Iohn Gell</hi> received Commiſſion to be Colonell, and then his endeavour was not wanting to the utmoſt of his power, to ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that great work, I mean the <hi>Militia,</hi> the ſetting whereof forward at the firſt was ſomething hard &amp; difficult, and the harder it was the more it makes for his honour, and I hope God will honour him for it; for thoſe that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God, he hath promiſed to honour them: After that he had broken the Ice, ſome others were willing to goe the ſame way; but it is thought by ſome, that had not he been active in the buſineſſe, the Commiſſion of Aray might have endangered both the Town and Countie, for it is too apparent, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards divers of our great men turned Array men: and ſome that wee thought would have been faithfull to us, by reaſon of their great proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but he that will proteſt he will go to <hi>London</hi> with ſpeed, and goes to <hi>Yorke,</hi> What thinke you by him? Or he that proteſts he will ſtand for the true Proteſtant Religion, and his actions manifeſt the contrarie? What think you by him? Surely I thinke you will hardly believe him, ſome ſuch as theſe I my ſelf am able to witneſſe againſt: The noble Colonell beginning to ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>Militia,</hi> I ſent unto him, that if he pleaſed, all the Armes I had and my ſelfe alſo were at his command; he indeed did not ſend for them, but after he came to Darbie to be reſident, ſome Captains under his command had them, ſo they are imployed in his Regiment. My next poore endeavour was to finde an horſe, and armes for his rider; after this being ſent a meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the Committee of Nottingham, and having diſpatched the thing I went about; One whom I do much honour, Mr. <hi>Iames Chadwick,</hi> told me he had a great deſire to ſpeak with me, ſaying that baſe Towne of Newark did much trouble him, and he had a great deſire to go to get ſome forces to joyne with them againſt it, he asked me if I would go with him to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, I anſwered him through the whole world, if God inable, for the advancemt of the cauſe: I alſo told him I had been lately at Mancheſter, and I heard there was a Regiment disbanded, partly for want of pay and partly for want of Imployment: The next morning wee went to Darbie, and he acquainted Colonell <hi>Gell</hi> with it, who highly approved of it, Sir ſaid I let us neglect no opportunity, there is a conſiderable force at Cheſterfield, &amp; a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of ſtout blades at Sheffield, and it is not much out of the way: he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to it, and we went to both places, and he wanted for no accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, in promiſe: but Sir, ſaid I, I cannot ſee how you can undertake a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of this nature, for if the Deſigne ſhould miſcarry, you will be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be queſtioned, except you have the approbation of my Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> he being Generall of the North, and ſaid, I hear he is not farre off, and it may be you may receive a greater accommodation there then you are aware of; ſaid he, thou ſayeſt well, but wilt thou undertake the buſineſſe at Mancheſter?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121230:4"/>Sir ſaid I, Take no care for that, for I am acquainted with many of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee there; ſo went thither and received an anſwer of a large accomodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, after one deſigne was paſt, ſo I returned to him to Sheffield, as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
            <p>The next newes I heard was, my Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> had given him Commiſſion to raiſe forces in any part of the North, there were divers Gentlemen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about that had raiſed forces for the preſervation of the Countrey, who took a love unto him and deſired he would be reſident with them, who were all willing to come under his command, ſo that by that meanes he had 1200. raiſed in a weekes ſpace, the like hath hardly been ſeen in any place, Sir ſaid I, ſeeing you have received ſo large accommodation, the Countrey will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect you ſhould doe them ſome good, moreover, I ſaid, here are two pettie Garriſons, Welbeck and Boulſover which trouble them, and there are two implacable enemies to the Truth, the Lord <hi>Davincourt,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Kingstone:</hi> pretend as you would go againſt Boulſover, and fall upon the E. of <hi>Davincourt,</hi> make him and his wealth ſure; and next pretend you will go againſt Welbeck, but fall upon the E. of <hi>Kingſtone,</hi> For truly ſaid I, if they be not looked unto in time, they will do a world of miſchiefe; He anwſered and ſaid it was his intent, but that he could not as yet ſet upon any Deſigne for want of Ordnance, whereupon he gave me a Diurnall of his Endeavours, how God had bleſſed him, and withall ſent me to Darbie, to Colonell <hi>Gell,</hi> who was not wanting to helpe forward ſo good a worke, for he ſent his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonell, two peeces of good Ordnance, and very nigh three hundred men.</p>
            <p>The deſigne being ſet upon, and Colonell Chadwick being on the top of Staley Hall, and ſeeing the Ordnance to give over playing, I praid him to ſend a meſſenger, he did ſo, and he brought newes that wee had ſome men ſlaine, and that my Lord had made his peace, and brought forth ſome four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore pounds, ſwearing it was all the money he had in the houſe, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of ſome two thouſand more, I proteſt ſaid I, this will prove a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond peece of Buſineſſe, for this will undoe all, for I will not give two pence for that promiſe, if my Lord goe to Newark: I pray you, ſaid I, let the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne be renewed againe, ſay but the word, and I will go and quarter all your men there all night, and we will ſeaze upon my Lords body, which will be much for the honour of the cauſe, and if we do not finde money and gold good ſtore, to helpe to maintaine the cauſe, never truſt me gaine: but it was not granted, then my Lord goes to Newarke, and three dayes after, ſends three Troopes of horſe and fetcht away eight or nine horſe-loads of money, gold and plate, that was hid hard by the Communion Table, it ſeemes ſome great men make an Altar of it, for it was partly laid Altar-wiſe, Alſo Boul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover Scouts fetcht away great ſtore of Bacon, Butter cheeſe and corne, which I would have had carried to our Garriſon at Cheſterfield, but it was not; the deſigne fel between two, where the fault was I can tel, let others judge, but had the L. <hi>Davencourt,</hi> and the Earl of Kingſton been made ſure, it had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter both for them and us, as the event ſince hath made it good but the pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Newark of <hi>Pueſey, Davincourt,</hi> and <hi>Kingſton,</hi> were as a Loadſtone,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121230:5"/>that drew ſo many great ones, and ſo much mony, gould and plate with them, that hath been the very ſubſiſtence of the towne, ſo that here you may ſee, that in the negligent doing of the work of God, in the ſparing of Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, we have been the beſt friends to that Town, and the worſt to our own Counties: After this Colonell <hi>Chadwick</hi> went to Nottingham to keep the Seſſions, and for Magazine, but ſad newes came, that the Earle of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtles Forces coming, and ours going unadviſedly againſt them, and wanting Orders and ski fall Commanders, were utterly ſurpriſed. Indeed I alwaies thought we ſhould be croſt in our proceedings, for I often deſired that the Word and the Sword might go together, but could not obtaine it, but great accommodation in the ſetting forward of great Deſignes, requires great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, and humiliation being joyned with the Sword, is the onely way to helpe forward a good cauſe, for thoſe that have entertained faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the keeping of this duty afoote, God hath bleſſed them the beſt in their undertakings, this is for the comfort of <hi>England,</hi> that God hath an humble and a praying people in it.</p>
            <p>After this a letter came from the Parliament, and the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> not onely a requeſt but a command for ſixe Counties to joyne together, which was one great and chiefe worke of the Kingdome: Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Chadwick</hi> conceiving it to bee a worke of ſuch great conſequence, as I my ſelfe ſaid, it was a chiefe deſigne of the Kingdome: and as I heard Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Gell</hi> ſay, that except that courſe was taken the Kingdome was in great danger to be brought to povertie: colonell <hi>Chadwicke</hi> having a great deſire to helpe forward this worke ſpared neither paines nor coſt, but went from Nottingham to Darbie, from darbie we went to Mancheſter, from thence to Nantwitch, and from thence to Stafford; and to Manceſter againe, and ſo to Nantwitch: But one countey promiſing large, and not performing, hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the worke for going forward. <hi>(Lankaſhire.)</hi> I pray God it be not laid to their charge; But when they have all done, to quit and demoliſh pettie Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, and to get into great bodies will be found the way to do the worke, and to ſave the Kingdome, for being undone: After that colonell Chad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick went to Leeke, where the they tooke a love to him, and defired him that he would be reſident with them, who granted unto them: but what was done from that time, til General <hi>Faireſax</hi> came to Leeke, I forbear to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, except, I be requeſted, we went along with the Generall to Mancheſter, who went to raiſe forces for the reliefe of Nantwitch, the countey did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate him, with a conſiderable force, two dayes were ſet apart toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for humiliation, and prayer, the third wee marched forward; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Randezvouze, nothing but praying and ſinging; not one oath that I heard in all the way, truly it thought I was the moſt comfortable time that ever I had ſince I went forth, although I lay upon the ground, and was glad to drink fair water; For Gods cauſe was proſecuted in his own way, and he bleſſed it accordingly, to the good of ſeverall counties, and the rejoycing of the Kingdome, my hearts deſire, and prayers to God, is for the Generall, for he is a true ſouldier of Ieſus CHRIST, and certainly he is guarded with a guard of Angels, God in mercy long preſerve him. The next day after the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121230:5"/>relieving of Nantwich, I was ſent a Meſſenger to ſome of the chief of them that belong to the Generall: After I had delivered the Meſſage, I requeſted I might move one thing unto them, which was this; Gentlemen, ſaid I, God hath made the Generall and you, all faithfull inſtruments for the good of the Country, for the relieving of the Town, and for the ſetling again of Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Brereton;</hi> but I fear except one thing be done, that is the demoliſhing of petty Gariſons, for after the Generall is gone out of theſe parts, they will endeavour the taking of them again, and then they will endeavour to glean up all the proviſion they can, between them and Nantwitch, that at the laſt, they will endanger to make them come forth for bread: But however you will acknowledge it a great mercy to have ſtrong holds delivered into your hands, then caſt your eyes upon this; We had Litchfield cloſe, Tutbury Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Chillington Houſe, Biddulph Hall, Winckfield Mannor, and Sheffild Mannor. Now judge you whether we have made uſe of Gods mercies or not; for had theſe been demoliſhed at the firſt when we had them, much bloud had been ſaved, which is and may be ſhed, many mens goods would have been ſaved, which are and may be taken; beſides, free Trading had been laid open betwixt the South and the North: And I am heartily ſorry, that the faithfull Citizens ſhould be ſo much prejudiced, through our negligence; for Trafficke is to the Kingdome partly as Water is to a Mill, take away the Water, and the Mill will do but little good: You ſee we have been the worſt Enemies in this, to our ſelves. Better it is that ſtrong Holds were demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, then the Kingdome endangered. For King <hi>Iames</hi> himſelf was once in that minde, I would King CHARLES were alſo, but I hope the Parliament will: For Caſtles or ſtrong Holds will do no good in this Kingdome, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting Port Towns, but ſpin out the Kingdomes miſery, eſpecially in theſe diſtracted times. Wherein you may ſee we have not made ſuch uſe of mercies as we might have done. God is ſaid, <hi>to curſe the ſtones and timber of the houſe where Idolatry is committed;</hi> but you may ſee what we have gotten by ſparing of them. He that ſeeks for a petty Gariſon, is either a Coward, or ſeeks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo farre as any man ſeeks himſelf, he is no friend to the Cauſe, King, Parliament, or Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Two dayes after, a Meſſenger came to Sir <hi>William Brereton</hi> and told him, that the Scots of a certain were come in, and ſaid that Generall <hi>Leſtey</hi> ſent unto Collonel <hi>Rigbey,</hi> that if there were any ſpeciall deſigne to ſet on, he would ſend ten thouſand with ſpeed, ſomething was ſaid. Gentlemen ſaid I, there is a great providence to be obſerved in this, for ten thouſand being with diſcretion conducted into Wales, will prove very ſerviceable; firſt, for the bringing in of thoſe malignant Counties, for the temper of the Welchmen is ſuch, that if a conſiderable force come amongſt them, they will ſide with them: Witneſſe Sir <hi>William Brereton</hi> that holy man, upon a ſmall entrance he made, how they came in to him, and condiſcended to a Weekly pay. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they vvill be ſerviceable to ſtop up the paſſages againſt the Iriſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels; for it is reported the Queen is going for them, and the Divell and all, to come to cut honeſt harmleſſe Proteſtants throates in England: if they come, I vvill vvarrant you the Divell vvill be conducter. Thirdly, they vvill
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121230:6"/>be ſerviceable in preventing Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> or any of the Popiſh Army, for ſecuring themſelves, or recruting themſelves in thoſe Counties, vvhich they ever have and vvill make the chiefeſt uſe of, if they be not prevented. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they vvill be ſerviceable if the Earle of Nevvcaſtles forces make a retreat out of the North, as it is thought that it being too hot for them, as I believe it begins to be, they vvill be ready to joyne vvith our forces, for the prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſpoiling of ſome Counties; If the North grovv too hot for him, vvhat do you think the South vvill do? But I vvill tell you, except he do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of the miſchief he hath done to the poore flock of Chriſt, he muſt have a hotter place then either of them.</p>
            <p>After this, I vvent to Stafford vvith an Order from the Generall; I moved a vvord or two concerning the demoliſhing of petty Gariſons; But noble Collonel <hi>Ridgley,</hi> being truly ſenſible of the Kingdomes miſery, made a ſhort Speech, vvhich he deſerves to be highly honoured for: After, I vvent a long journey to know the truth, concerning the people that I have long ſince ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken much of, the people of my deſire, the people of my delight; I mean, the honeſt Scots, vvhich are the noble Philadelphians: for the Relation, I forbear till hereafter. Being imployed as a Meſſenger, and having been reſident in ſeverall Counties, ſome things I have obſerved; I vvill relate but little. I have heard many aſperſions caſt on Colonell <hi>Gell,</hi> but he hath acted like a Souldier, and in the laſt concluſion, he will get more honour, than many that I know, whoſe names I forbeare to relate, becauſe of their honeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; For they that will think to ſave a Countrey in a time of War, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out raiſing men and money, doth as a man that takes in hand to build an houſe without either wood or ſtone:</p>
            <p>For Nottingham they have not been wanting according to their ſtrength, being almoſt ſurrounded with the Enemie, they have received ſome loſſe, but I hope God in mercy will make it up again; for the love that I beare to that towne, I could wiſh that the great Army that lay ſo long there the laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and did ſo little good, had ſpared the Towne and quartered their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my about Newarke, God in mercy ſend good Commanders in chiefe, that may faithfully ſet forward the worke with ſpeed: For the right Honourable the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and that faithfull ſouldier of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, who is able to expreſſe their zeale, their courage and their Faithfulneſſe, to the Cauſe, and to ſeverall counties, God in mercy preſerve them, and I truſt ere long he will give them their hearts deſire: And For Mancheſter, God was pleaſed to make an handfull of people to ſtand againſt a potent Enemie, and to make them the chief Inſtruments, for the incouragement, in the ſetting forward of the <hi>Militia,</hi> let them be highly honoured for their workes ſake; For Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> he hath been a faithfull Inſtrument of much good, God in mercy bring him ſafe againe into the County, for I doubt there vvill bee need of him: For Stafford I leave it to the judgement of Colonell <hi>Greaves,</hi> and others: For the honeſt and willing Morelanders, They have fermerly ſuffered ſore loſſe, not for the want of honeſt, but carefull and skilfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, but this is for their comfort, they have gotten more then they have loſt, and in time no doubt but God will teach their hands to War, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121230:6"/>their fingers to fight: I will tell you now what I could deſire, it is that the King would be pleaſed to ſeale an Act for the baniſhment of Papiſts and for the bringing of the great Incendiaries of the kingdome to condigne puniſhment, and then who will not beleeve what the King hath proteſted.</p>
            <p>I could deſire alſo that they that have taken up armes aginſt this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet profeſſe themſelves to ſtand for the Proteſtant Religion, that they would reſtore honeſt people and faithfull Miniſters to their own cures and habitations, and then we will have a charitable conceit of them, that they ſtand for the proteſtant religion, but not before: I could alſo deſire that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Haſtings</hi> would give the firſt preſident, becauſe his Fathers houſe hath bin ſo hnourable for Religion, witneſſe Mr. <hi>Elderſham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Aſh,</hi> and divers others, and that he would no longer diſhonour that which God hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued, and that Aſhbee which is now a cage of uncleane ſpirits, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a place for Gods people to aſſemble in as it hath been heretofore: I have knowne him a good Inſtrument for the good of the Common-wealth, and I hope God will open his eyes, and make him one for the Church, I have heard many a prayer put up for him, and I have heard many pray that if they were ordained to be taken priſoners, they might fall into his hands, for the mercy that he hath ſhewed to honeſt priſoners, I hope God will ſhew mercy to him, for the promiſe is, <hi>that the mercifull ſhall obtain mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> I have heard many ſay, he is the greateſt plunderer in the Kingdome, but give me leave to ſpeak one word for him; he hath done it by vertue of a Proclamation ſet forth by the King; But when open warr is proclaimed againſt an Honourable Parliament, and proclamations iſſued forth, for taking of honeſt mens goods, that the Kings beſt ſubjects cannot have free traffique one with another, theſe things cannot but procure a judgement, but woe be to the authors; they ſay plaine dealing is the beſt, then I will tell you that there is more Noble and Gentile Theves made in <hi>England,</hi> the laſt yeere and this, then ever there were before, but who made them, be angry with me, if I do not tell you: But there is ſome hopes, that that may be made good which is ſpoken in a paſſage by Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> that God will make King Charles a chiefe inſtrument to give the Pope a deadly blow, you know there hath many a petition been put up to his Majeſtie; and I am ſure there hath been many a faithfull praier put up to the Lord of Hoſtes for him: If he forſake the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and returne to his great Counſell, and all thoſe that profeſſe themſelves to ſtand for the proteſtant Religion, would joyne themſelves in ſincerity and truth of heart, with our loving brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> according to their loving invitation, in their laſt Remonſtrance; Do not doubt of it, but the Pope will have ſuch a blowe, as he dare never looke up again in <hi>England;</hi> now what do you thinke is worthy to be done to all thoſe that will not helpe forward ſo good a worke; as Newters, and the Prelaticall faction, and thoſe Muck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes that thinke to get all by following their callings in theſe diſtracted times, and cannot be content but they muſt be pratling againſt the faithfull Citizens, and honeſt men in the Countrey, that are willing to ſpare neither time nor paines, nor lives nor eſtates, but to lay downe all for this Cauſe, that will be ſaying its fitter for them to be following of their Callings at home,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121230:7"/>and looke to thier wives and Children, but they would be taught what Chriſt ſaith: <hi>That he that loves father or mother, or Wife, or children, or lands, or livings, or life it ſelf better then him, is not worthy of him;</hi> and what <hi>David</hi> ſaid when he was going to fiht, and his brethren, ſaid as theſe men do, that it was fitter for him to follow his calling in tending of his fathers ſheepe, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſaid unto them, is there not a cauſe? Doth not now lives and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and all that true Chriſtians have, lie at the ſtake? And is there not a cauſe? So the true calling of a Chriſtian is to vindicate this Cauſe to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his power, and ability, Chriſt ſaith that he that is not with him, is aginſt him, and truely if Ordinances of Parliament, had been better executed in ſetthing forward of the Covenant, and ſome other things, we might more cleerely have ſeen by this time, who had been for Chriſt, and who againſt him. It hath been a trouble unto me in ſome places where I have been, and a Committee of Parliament there preſent, and yet theſe things neglected, the life of the Lawes and ordinances lies in the Execution of them, I would I could ſee the neglecters puniſhed, that do not execute the Parliaments com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, according to the utmoſt of their power: in many places where I have been, I have heard ſome to deſire peace, almoſt on any tearmes, ſome againe have deſired peace with holineſſe, or no peace, for the firſt, if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament would have had peace with Monopolizers, Papiſts, the Prelaticall Faction, and the great Incendiaries of the Kingdome, the firſt had had their deſire, but it is the ſecond that muſt have their deſire, for let them not doubt but God will make this Parliament chief inſtruments that they may injoy Chriſt in the puritie of his Ordinances, and then they will have a tenfold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall for all their faithfull endeavours, for whom God gives Chriſt unto, with him he gives them all things, for Chriſt is all things to all them than truely do injoy him.</p>
            <p>And you, Noble, Faithfull and true hearted Citizens, that have been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to purchaſe the truth at any rate, chere up your ſpirits, for ſure your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing draweth neere. I have heard many accuſing the King for having the papiſts in his Army, and I thinke not without cauſe, and alſo the Parliament for having the Separates in their Army, For the Papiſts, I hope it will not be long before an order be taken with them, and if there be any that will deny the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be a true Church, as it ſtands joyned to the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in worſhip and diſcipline, it being judged to be the beſt reformed Church in the World; I hope the Parliament wil take an Order with them, but give me leave to ſpeak one word for thoſe that have been called Separates under the Prelaticall governement, you know there was ſo much rubbiſh brought into the church, that tender Conſciences could hardly get into it, but bleſſed be God, this Parliament having made an Ordinance for the taking of all things out of the Church that are offenſiue, and wee being joyned to the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Diſcipline, Worſhip, and Government, I cannot ſee that any can lawfully abſent themſelves from that aſſemblie, where this is performed, but I will tell you, what I could deſire, and it may pleaſe God that ſome good effect may be produced by it: It is that every faithfull Miniſter would refuſe that call which he had by the Biſhops, and be willing to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121230:7"/>called by the faithfull congregation, or a ſelected company choſen for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>I could alſo deſire, that where the Miniſter is called, a day of humiliation may be ſet apart; That God would be pleaſed to inable him with guilts, for the faithfull diſcharge of his place: And whereas it is ſaid that Churches were builded by Papiſts, and God is ſaid to curſe the ſtones and timber of the houſe where Idolatry hath been committed, that God would be pleaſed to ſanctifie that place for his own worſhip; for it is ſaid, <hi>That all things are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by the Word and Prayer.</hi> So that where theſe things are performed, what is worthy to be done to them, that will abſent themſelves from that Aſſembly?</p>
            <p>Surely, it will not be ill taken, to deſire that a ſpeciall care may be taken for the ſetling of a faithfull Miniſtry, and that rather a place may ſtand void, then be imployed by an inſufficient Miniſter. Land had better be untild, then to be plowed and then ſown with that which is naught. And that care may be taken for the maintainance of the Miniſtery, that he that hath the leaſt, may have ſufficient. That in every particular County, thoſe which are called Church-livings, as Prebendaries, Parſonages, Vicarages, Tithes, Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all of that nature, faithfull men may be choſen to collect into one; and out of that the Miniſtery to have ſufficient maintainance eſtabliſhed, and the reſt to be imployed for good and profitable uſes: As the maintaining a Navie on the Sea, or the bringing up or putting forth of poor Orphans, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſtocks for the imployment of the poor, or in danger of a forraign inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: So will that which hath been ill imployed be well imployed, ſo will frivolous ſutes be prevented betwixt Miniſter and people, and ſo will the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery have nothing to care for, but to feed the flock of Chriſt, of whom they are made overſeers. So will the Goſpell flouriſh, ſo will the hearts of Gods people be chereed, ſo will God be glorified, ſo will the Lord delight in us, he will love us freely, he will heal our backſlidings, he will dwell in the middeſt of us, and do us good.</p>
            <p>I could deſire that all true Chriſtians would give the Lord no reſt, till the platform and diſcipline of the Church be eſtabliſhed, according to the rule of CHRIST, then would it go well with the Church, and when it goes well the Church, it will go well with the Commonwealth, but not before; ſo will the Lord make his promiſe good unto us, and our poſterity after us, and our ſeed ſhall injoy the bleſſing.</p>
            <p>I have heard ſome ſay, it is not poſſible that ever we ſhould ſee good days, till the King return to the Parliament; But know this, that there is nothing impoſſible with God: The Parliament being the repreſentative Body of the whole Kingdome, it will be proved the King is preſent with them, and what both the houſes do conclude on, it may be truly ſaid to be the Kings own act: The compariſon will not hold, which I heard made by a Miniſter in Derb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in his Pulpit, where he compared the King to the Sun, and the Parliament to a company of dark confuſed ſtars, that have no light but what they borrow from the Sun: He was active alſo in reading the prayer againſt our loving bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in Scotland; but from ſuch preaching and ſuch praying, the Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121230:8"/>me, and God in mercy make the King, as a Sun to cheer up and revive the hearts of his poor people, in theſe dark and ſad times, and as a ſhield to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the true Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>I will tell you ſtill what I could deſire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if I deſire amiſſe, I pray you pardon me; for it is from a heart ſenſible of the Kingdoms miſery, and in love to the Cauſe that the Parliament vindicates, which is for the Truth; It is, that in all Counties, when we are Maſters of the field, there may be choſen a faithfull Generall or Commander in chief, and in every Hundreth, an able Colonel, and Captains proportionable, ſuch as the Country is willing to approve of, and to venture their lives with; and that all that profeſſe themſelves to ſtand for the Cauſe, may be liſted under thoſe Commanders the neareſt reſiding to them; being all ingaged in the cauſe, it being the publike cauſe, and that they may not lye by great companies in Gariſon Townes (eſpecially in Summer aime) to conſume the Kingdomes money, but that there may be preparation for ſeverall Counties to joyn together in Aſſociation, with wiſdome and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, in prayer and humiliation, and that we may come forth with zeale and courage to help the Lord againſt the mighty: And alſo that the covenant may be ſet forward with ſpeed, the neglecters puniſhed, and refuſers, made known; that ſo our loving brethren that are come ſo willingly to help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the work of Reformation, which may be ſaid to be next to the worke of Creation may ſee more cleerly how to proceed; that ſo the Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcowred of Idolatry, Superſtition, and Will-worſhip, and Chriſt ſet up in the purity of his Ordinances, then will the promiſe be made good; which is, of a new heaven, and a new earth, wherein dwels righteouſneſſe; and then will the honeſt Proteſtants, that have been willing to lay down all for this cauſe, take up the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſing aloud the falvation of their God. I would deſire one thing more, it is that the Book ſet forth by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament, be read once a Week in our Army, for regulating our forces, and the puniſhing of offences both in Commanders and ſouldiers, may be made more uſe of. For in ſome places it hath not been ſet forward, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proteſtation, nor Covenant; and that a Committee of Parliament and commanders there reſident, I could deſire that commanders would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to reform themſelves, and then our Armies would be better reformed, and ſome more time ſpared out of the Ale-houſe for exerciſe in the houſe of God, and in the field; So ſhould our campes be purged, then we ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry none of our <hi>Achans</hi> into the campe, our loving brethren, whereby the worke may be hindered.</p>
            <p>I will tell you that they I have ſo much ſpoken of, that the work could not be done without them, ſo long deſired and prayed for, I mean the noble <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphians,</hi> are now come into England. The Lord of Hoſts in mercy be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire by night, and direct them that they may carry themſelves ſo in this weighty buſineſſe, that all the black mouths which have been opened ſo wide againſt them, may be ſtopped. If I ſhould tell you that God will make our loving Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> unto <hi>England,</hi> as a skilful Phyſitian unto a groſſe body, to purge out the corrupt humours, or as Refiners of the droſſe from the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121230:8"/>gold, you wil hardly beleeve it. Or if I ſhould tel you of a warre of Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that God in mercy to his own people, and in juſtice to the wicked, hath ſent and called in <hi>England</hi> a great grand-Jury, to inquire out new Sences, troublers of the Church and Common-wealth, diſturbers of Gods people, and and that faithfull Miniſters and honeſt people, muſt give informations; you wil hardly beleeve it. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Timo trieth all things,</hi> beleeve it as you finde it. Surely it wil not be denied but all thoſe that are Enemies to this glorious work of Reformation, ought to be inquired after, as Papiſts and the Prelatical faction, and the Incendiaries of the Kingdome, and after ſuch as have ſpoken more or leſſe againſt this honourable Parliament, and after ſuch as are deſpiſers or evil-ſpeakers againſt our loving brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and why not after all ſuch as have received Commiſſions, and have been active in nothing but for their own ends in ſeazing upon Papiſts and malignants goods, and it may be honeſt mens too, without order from the Committee or the chief commanders from whom they received their commiſſion, and have not brought in ſuch goods to the publike ſtock, but have converted them to their own private uſe; becauſe that, that which ought to be imployed in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cauſe, ought not to be converted to a private uſe. And after all ſuch, whoſe actions makes it manifeſt, that their deſires are to ſpin out the Kingdoms mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; as all theſe have done unto others, ſo let it be done unto them: Curſed be he that doth the work of the Lord deceitfully, and curſed be he that keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth back his ſword from bloud: <hi>Ier.</hi> 47. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>I ſay unto you, get into the Covenant whilſt you may, if you profeſſe your ſelves for the truth, leſt it fall out with you as it did with them in the old World: For you ſhal ſee ere long that the Cavaliers wil leave the word Roundheads, and call us Covenanters, for in calling of us Roundheads, they do but proclaim themſelves fooles; as thoſe do that gave their Votes for the election of this honourable Parliament that ſtands for the truth, and ſince have opened their mouthes wide againſt them: And for thoſe that are run away from the truth, I pray you tell me if you think that thoſe be not fools.</p>
            <p>I need not tel you that there are great Armies prepared and preparing, but I am perſwaded that they are not only to knock the Pope out of England, but Ireland, and France, and Rome, and ſend him halting to Avanion, whither ſome of the Papiſts may follow him like bloud-hounds by the footing, to mourn over his buriall.</p>
            <p>Of all things that I have deſired, I pray you let this be granted, that the duty of humiliation and prayer be not neglected, pray for King <hi>Charles,</hi> that God would make him a faithful inſtrument for his glory, and the good of this Kingdome, and that he would be pleaſed to take him out of the hands of his and the Kingdomes Enemies, and ſend him ſafe to his honourable Parliament; and pray for our loving brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> whom it pleaſed God to make ſuch faithful inſtruments for the cal of this Parliament, that God would be pleaſed ever to protect them, and direct them; and pray for the faithful Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, whom God hath been pleaſed to make ſo faithful to the Parliament to the King, and Kingdome. Bleſſed are they that pray for the peace of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:121230:9"/>and I am ſure that they muſt be bleſſed that pray and bend the utmoſt of their endeavours for an holy peace in England, Peace with Holineſſe the Lord ſend us: Souldiers be content with your wages, and away with this baſe plundering; what you get from the Enemy with your ſword is your own, but if you ſeize upon Papiſts or Malignants goods, bring it into the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſtock; for that which ſhould be ſpent in a publike cauſe, ought not to be converted to a private uſe. But you will ſay you have no wages: I will tell you what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Having food and raiment therewith be content,</hi> never deſert a good cauſe for want of pay. Are we not all, and all that we have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the cauſe? Eſtates and and Liberties, and Lives, and Religion, doth not al lye at the ſtake? Stand for CHRIST and for his cauſe and he wil ſtand for you, for be you ſure he wil be a better paymaſter unto you then al the world can afford; for his promiſe is, be faithful unto death and he wil give you a crown of Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For my part my poore endeavours have not been wanting ever ſince the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia was ſet forward, neither ſhall it ever be wanting, God willing, ſo long as life and eſtate ſhall last, I never deſired pay but the Parliaments faith, and now I have more then I did deſire, for there is a promiſe made by both Kingdomes, that all that endeavour to bee active and faithfull to this cauſe ſhall be no looſers, ſo that this promiſe and the promiſe by Chriſt, is ſufficient to incourage all men that either have or will take up armes in this cauſe:</hi> The poore endeavours and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of one that earneſtly deſires the advancement of the cauſe of Chriſt, <hi>the yeer</hi> 1644. <hi>wherin the troubles, and the troublers of the Church and Common-Wealth will be in turning ore. I could deſire to be ſatiſfied in this, whether we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Prelaticall governement were not the luke-warme</hi> Laodiceans, <hi>and alſo in this, that we now being joyned to the</hi> Philadelpians, <hi>in Diſcipline, Worſhip Governement and Covenant, and made one with them, and they with us, whether if we were</hi> Laodiceans, <hi>we be not now made</hi> Philadelphians: <hi>But I will hearken to the faithfull Miniſterie, and if it prove truth, then</hi> (<hi>ſee</hi> England <hi>is Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphized) and I will ſay to thoſe that are in Covenant, ſtand to it you couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Philadelphians, <hi>for God will give you to poſſeſſe the very Gates of your one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and we ſhall ſee that the Parliament hath made uſe of thoſe words, namely to buy the truth at any rate, and that the field is purchaſed for us, where the precious pearle lyeth. I meane the pure Ordinances of of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>but I will waite.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
